Some people think that there's a TED Talk formula:
有人认为TED演讲有一个固定模式：
"Give a talk on a round, red rug."
“站在一块圆形的红地毯上。”
"Share a childhood story."
“分享童年的经历。”
"Divulge a personal secret."
“分享个人的秘密。”
"End with an inspiring call to action."
“最后号召大家行动起来。”
No.
不是的。
That's not how to think of a TED Talk.
我们不该这么来看待TED演讲。
In fact, if you overuse those devices,
实际上，如果滥用这些手法，
you're just going to come across as clichéd or emotionally manipulative.
只会给人留下陈词滥调 或者心灵鸡汤的感觉。
But there is one thing that all great TED Talks have in common,
但所有优秀的TED演讲 确实有一个共同点，
and I would like to share that thing with you,
这也是我想和各位分享的，
because over the past 12 years, I've had a ringside seat,
因为12年来我一直坐在场边,
listening to many hundreds of amazing TED speakers, like these.
聆听了数百位演讲者的 精彩演讲，比如他们。
I've helped them prepare their talks for prime time,
我协助他们准备演讲， 在黄金时段播出，
and learned directly from them
也从他们那里学到了
their secrets of what makes for a great talk.
做一场精彩演讲的秘诀。
And even though these speakers and their topics all seem
尽管这些演讲者和他们的演讲主题
completely different,
都各不相同，
they actually do have one key common ingredient.
但有一个关键点是相同的。
And it's this:
那就是：
Your number one task as a speaker
作为演讲者最重要的任务
is to transfer into your listeners' minds an extraordinary gift --
是送给你的听众一件特别的礼物——
a strange and beautiful object that we call an idea.
它神奇而美丽， 我们称之为“想法”。
Let me show you what I mean.
下面我来解释一下。
Here's Haley.
这是海利。
She is about to give a TED Talk
她将要进行一个TED演讲,
and frankly, she's terrified.
坦白说，她很紧张。
(Video) Presenter: Haley Van Dyck!
（视频）主持人：海利·范·戴克！
(Applause)
（掌声）
Over the course of 18 minutes,
在18分钟的演讲过程中，
1,200 people, many of whom have never seen each other before,
此前互不相识的1200名听众
are finding that their brains are starting to sync with Haley's brain
发现自己的思维渐渐与海利同步，
and with each other.
与其他人同步。
They're literally beginning to exhibit the same brain-wave patterns.
甚至可以说，他们的 脑电波都开始同步。
And I don't just mean they're feeling the same emotions.
他们当时不仅感受相同。
There's something even more startling happening.
还有更令人吃惊的事在发生。
Let's take a look inside Haley's brain for a moment.
让我们到海利的大脑中看一看。
There are billions of interconnected neurons in an impossible tangle.
数十亿神经元相互连接，互相缠绕。
But look here, right here --
但是看这里，
a few million of them are linked to each other
其中几百万个神经元连接在一起，
in a way which represents a single idea.
形成了一个想法。
And incredibly, this exact pattern is being recreated in real time
难以置信的是，同样的连接方式，
inside the minds of everyone listening.
也同时在每一位听众的 脑海中出现了。
That's right; in just a few minutes,
是的，几分钟内，
a pattern involving millions of neurons
这种包含几百万神经元的 特殊连接模式
is being teleported into 1,200 minds,
仅仅通过听和看，
just by people listening to a voice and watching a face.
就传递进了1200个大脑之中。
But wait -- what is an idea anyway?
那么，到底什么是想法呢？
Well, you can think of it as a pattern of information
你可以理解为是一种信息的组合，
that helps you understand and navigate the world.
能帮你理解和探索这个世界。
Ideas come in all shapes and sizes,
想法是多种多样的，
from the complex and analytical
有的复杂，有的简单，
to the simple and aesthetic.
有的理性，有的感性。
Here are just a few examples shared from the TED stage.
下面我举几个例子， 都发生在TED讲台上。
Sir Ken Robinson -- creativity is key to our kids' future.
肯·罗宾逊爵士——创造力 是决定孩子未来的关键。
(Video) Sir Ken Robinson: My contention is that creativity now
（视频）肯·罗宾逊爵士： 我认为在教育中，
is as important in education as literacy,
培养创造力和教读书写字一样重要，
and we should treat it with the same status.
我们应该同样重视。
Chris Anderson: Elora Hardy -- building from bamboo is beautiful.
伊劳拉·哈迪—— 竹制建筑的魅力。
(Video) Elora Hardy: It is growing all around us,
（视频）伊劳拉·哈迪： 竹子随处可见，
it's strong, it's elegant, it's earthquake-resistant.
很牢固，很优雅，可以抵御地震。
CA: Chimamanda Adichie -- people are more than a single identity.
奇麻曼达·阿迪契—— 人类并不只有单一属性。
(Video) Chimamanda Adichie: The single story creates stereotypes,
（视频）奇麻曼达·阿迪契： 单一的故事会导致片面，
and the problem with stereotypes is not that they are untrue,
片面的问题并不在于它不正确，
but that they are incomplete.
而在于它不完整。
CA: Your mind is teeming with ideas,
你的大脑里充满了各种想法，
and not just randomly.
它们并不是随机的，
They're carefully linked together.
而是相互联系的。
Collectively they form an amazingly complex structure
它们汇集成神奇而复杂的体系，
that is your personal worldview.
形成你的世界观。
It's your brain's operating system.
是你大脑的操作系统。
It's how you navigate the world.
也是你探索世界的方式。
And it is built up out of millions of individual ideas.
是数百万个想法的大集合。
So, for example, if one little component of your worldview
比如说，你世界观中的一小部分
is the idea that kittens are adorable,
告诉你小猫很可爱，
then when you see this,
那么当你看到小猫时，
you'll react like this.
你就会抚摸它。
But if another component of your worldview
而另一部分告诉你
is the idea that leopards are dangerous,
美洲豹很危险，
then when you see this,
那么当你看见它时，
you'll react a little bit differently.
你可能会撒腿就跑。
So, it's pretty obvious
所以显而易见，
why the ideas that make up your worldview are crucial.
这些想法对于塑造你的 世界观至关重要。
You need them to be as reliable as possible -- a guide,
它们就像一名值得信赖的向导，
to the scary but wonderful real world out there.
帮你应对这个美妙却又危险的世界。
Now, different people's worldviews can be dramatically different.
不同人的世界观截然不同。
For example,
举个例子，
how does your worldview react when you see this image:
你对下面的视频会有什么反应？
(Video) Dalia Mogahed: What do you think when you look at me?
（视频）达利亚·莫佳德： 你看到我的时候你在想什么？
"A woman of faith," "an expert," maybe even "a sister"?
“有信仰的女人”，“专家” 甚至是“姐姐”？
Or "oppressed," "brainwashed,"
或者“受压迫的”，“被洗脑的”
"a terrorist"?
还是“恐怖分子”？
CA: Whatever your answer,
无论你的答案是什么，
there are millions of people out there who would react very differently.
成千上万的人， 就会有成千上万种答案。
So that's why ideas really matter.
正因为此，想法才非常重要。
If communicated properly, they're capable of changing, forever,
通过正确的交流，想法可以永远地
how someone thinks about the world,
改变一个人的世界观，
and shaping their actions both now and well into the future.
影响他们现在和未来的的行为。
Ideas are the most powerful force shaping human culture.
想法是塑造人类文化 最强大的力量。
So if you accept
如果你认同，
that your number one task as a speaker is to build an idea
演讲者最重要的 任务是提出一个想法，
inside the minds of your audience,
并让听众认同，
here are four guidelines for how you should go about that task:
那么这里有四条原则你可以遵循：
One, limit your talk to just one major idea.
第一，让你的演讲主题明确。
Ideas are complex things;
想法是复杂的，
you need to slash back your content so that you can focus
你要避免长篇大论，专注于
on the single idea you're most passionate about,
最让你激动不已的那个想法，
and give yourself a chance to explain that one thing properly.
并想办法把它解释清楚。
You have to give context, share examples, make it vivid.
你需要解释背景， 举例说明，娓娓道来。
So pick one idea,
所以只挑选一个想法，
and make it the through-line running through your entire talk,
让它贯穿你的整个演讲，
so that everything you say links back to it in some way.
让你讲的所有内容都能与之呼应。
Two, give your listeners a reason to care.
第二，吸引你的听众。
Before you can start building things inside the minds of your audience,
在你将自己的想法灌输给观众之前，
you have to get their permission to welcome you in.
你必须得到他们的允许。
And the main tool to achieve that?
那主要手段是什么呢？
Curiosity.
好奇心。
Stir your audience's curiosity.
勾起观众的好奇心。
Use intriguing, provocative questions
提一些耐人寻味，引人入胜的问题
to identify why something doesn't make sense and needs explaining.
让大家发现有些事情 不合理，需要解释。
If you can reveal a disconnection in someone's worldview,
如果你让某人发现， 他的世界观里有空白，
they'll feel the need to bridge that knowledge gap.
他们就会想把这缺口补上。
And once you've sparked that desire,
一旦你勾起他们的求知欲，
it will be so much easier to start building your idea.
灌输你的想法就容易多了。
Three, build your idea, piece by piece,
第三，构筑你的想法， 一步一步来，
out of concepts that your audience already understands.
要使用观众已经了解的概念。
You use the power of language
用语言的力量，
to weave together concepts that already exist
把观众脑海中已经存在的概念
in your listeners' minds --
重新整合——
but not your language, their language.
不过要用观众能懂的语言。
You start where they are.
你要让他们跟上你的节奏。
The speakers often forget that many of the terms and concepts they live with
演讲者经常会忘记， 自己每天接触的术语和概念，
are completely unfamiliar to their audiences.
在观众们眼中可能就是天书。
Now, metaphors can play a crucial role in showing how the pieces fit together,
因此，善用比喻非常重要，
because they reveal the desired shape of the pattern,
因为比喻是用听众已经了解的概念，
based on an idea that the listener already understands.
来勾画缺失的那一块知识拼图。
For example, when Jennifer Kahn
比如，当珍妮弗·卡恩
wanted to explain the incredible new biotechnology called CRISPR,
想解释一种叫做CRISPR的 最前端的生物技术时，
she said, "It's as if, for the first time,
她说：“这项技术，就像你第一次
you had a word processor to edit DNA.
拥有了一台可以编辑DNA的 文字处理机一样。
CRISPR allows you to cut and paste genetic information really easily."
CRISPR能让你十分轻松的 剪切和粘贴基因组信息。”
Now, a vivid explanation like that delivers a satisfying aha moment
就这样，一个生动的描述， 让我们恍然大悟，
as it snaps into place in our minds.
并且深深地印在了我们的脑海里。
It's important, therefore, to test your talk on trusted friends,
在信任的朋友面前 试讲一下是很关键的，
and find out which parts they get confused by.
你可以找出他们 听不懂的地方（加以修改）。
Four, here's the final tip:
第四条，也是最后一条：
Make your idea worth sharing.
确定你的想法值得分享。
By that I mean, ask yourself the question:
我的意思是，扪心自问：
"Who does this idea benefit?"
“这个想法对谁有好处？”
And I need you to be honest with the answer.
你需要实事求是。
If the idea only serves you or your organization,
如果这个想法只服务于你或者你的组织，
then, I'm sorry to say, it's probably not worth sharing.
那么对不起，它也许不值得分享。
The audience will see right through you.
观众也马上能发现这一点。
But if you believe that the idea has the potential
但如果你认为自己的想法
to brighten up someone else's day
有可能照亮他人的人生，
or change someone else's perspective for the better
或者改善他人的观点，
or inspire someone to do something differently,
或者激励他人去改变，
then you have the core ingredient to a truly great talk,
那么你就拥有了 一篇精彩演讲的核心元素，
one that can be a gift to them and to all of us.
所有人都会因此受益。